all right I have a scary story uh about
free code camp and before I tell you
this story I want you to
understand that I think any resource
that you learn from no matter what is a
good thing and everybody's got a
different learning style they've got a
different uh you know approach to to
both teaching it as well as to learning
it obviously I have a very quirky weird
St I'm wearing a hoodie for God's sake
um you know and so I I have to be
careful because what I'm going to say is
going to sound extremely critical of of
fre code camp and it is
critical um of it and but I I want to
back it up um so this this video is is
going to be linked both from the web
part as well as from kind of the where
should I learn who should I learn from
part but um I was reminded of the story
today when we were doing web development
and um I mentioned um casually that
after learning the basic structure of a
website that I used to give people a
sort of a challenge and I would say okay
we next now next week when you come back
um let's have you let's see let's time
you let's see how long it takes you to
make a web page from scratch and I used
to always have Jokers you know come in
and do HTML 5 and then use the template
from from uh vs code and it would
autocomplete and they'd say I'm done Mr
Rob and I was like no you can't use that
you got to actually do it from scratch
and that meant that they had to remember
how to what how to do the elements in
order how to you know what they were you
know what the head and the body were
different and maybe you know put a
paragraph tag in there and it's kind of
a fun way informally to test them and
have them see how much they learn um and
it is actually one of those things where
kind of memorizing it makes makes sense
right because you don't always have
access to AI or to uh you know to a
template system is going to fill it out
for you it is true that memorizing
things like how do I start doing
anything any kind of boiler plate is
completely uh being replaced by AI
helping us create the boiler plate for
everything and that's awesome but but
the point of that particular exercise
was just to help them get to know it and
but that's not even really the main
point of this video um the main point of
this video is how little these people
learned from free code Camp um so I am
very sad to say that I I I I'm going to
share with you the statistics it's going
to look very bad on me and there's going
to be one person in the comments that's
going to say well that's just because
you're a sucky teacher or a bad
Mentor fine if you want to say that
great I'm still going to tell you the
story so I took 35 or 40 people that I
was mentoring and one year I said look I
am tired of Reinventing the will on
everything I want to get behind the
efforts of others that are that are
promoting education out there and and so
I sent all 40 40 45 people from my that
particular Mentor semester through freec
code Camp's web development project and
every week we would go through it and I
would help them do their things and I
had a couple people figure out how to
hack up hack the things so they could
get credit even though they didn't do it
which was totally cool um but I was like
you're not learning it just cuz you
learned how to hack it and it was really
funny um that's what happens when you
teach everybody to think like a hacker I
mean they're like how can I pass this
without having anyway so so they ended
up doing um you know they did go through
the thing but the problem and and honest
to God I don't know exact my best guess
uh about the problem with with the the
the web development certificate and they
all got the certificate they all all 45
or so of them got the certificate so
they were all officially web developers
according to free code camp and and so I
decided to test them I gave them the
challenge that I just mentioned to you I
gave them the challenge I said and they
came in one day after they had their
certificates and they printed it out and
they were showing it to their parents
and their parents thought they were
awesome parents love flashy pieces of
paper and t-shirts and crap like that
they don't when you when the parents
says what is my kid going to get I say
they're going to get knowledge and
learning potentially a job they're like
oh but do they get a certificate or do
they get something they get a trophy
they get something I can show the other
parents how awesome my kid is it was a
challenge it was a challenge and free
Cod Camp definitely did that free Cod
Camp gave him these big fantasy
certificate saying they were web
developers and and and you know and it
was like signed and they printed it out
and they hung it in their
room and then I tested them on
it do you know where this story is going
right not no that's not true two two of
them out of all of the 45 or so of these
kids could could finish making a web
page at all on their own only two of
them they went through the entire thing
they had a certificate and I sat them
down and I said fine make me a web page
and they couldn't do it they had no idea
and I like okay well let's do this let's
at least get to a server because PR Cod
Camp doesn't teach you how to set up a
live server so you can preview your site
at all it makes you completely dependent
on their service in order to even view
anything it doesn't talk about how to
make a web server it doesn't talk about
where you could host on get up for free
it doesn't talk about about how to
preview your stuff in real-time live
none of that none of that was covered
did it cover the meta tag yeah it
did but not a single one of these people
could create a website not none of them
and I kept saying okay I'm going to get
you a little bit of help here okay so
here you got a server now all right
ready go and I sent I said look okay you
got your server now all I want you to do
is just make a basic web document with
like a header of the title and one
paragraph and none of them can do it
except for two and the two that had were
able to do it were those who I already
taken through this Challenge and I had
taught him the things myself one at a
time in a thing and this isn't about me
this is about the dependability of for
Education
websites the the takeaway from this is
that in my experience four education
tools suck they totally suck and they
don't teach you actual skills they teach
you the theory or they get you to do a
thing but they they didn't even know
what index on HTML I'm not even kidding
my friends my friends I am not making
this up not none of these people none of
these people knew what to name the file
they didn't even know what the file was
or where it would go or why is it ending
with
HTML they may have known one or two or
three or the tags that was in in this
was in
201 19 that was in
2019 now is it true that free code Camp
has probably improved their materials a
lot since then yes it is um another one
was code academy code academy same exact
problem I sent people through there
couldn't do it either um and that was
when I realized and and this this really
is the takeaway the takeaway is that for
Education
simulations constantly suffer from
missing all of the
material right and and I my personal
theory on the free c-amp approach was
number one it wasn't based on any
pedagogy that has ever worked in an IT
sector period it was just based on okay
we're going to do this thing and then it
would immediately send them another
video and another thing and they would
do what was necessary to pass that level
and it it didn't it didn't add on to the
previous knowledge it just kept giving
them new knowledge without reinforcing
their old knowledge you know what would
have reinforced their old knowledge the
whole time by making an actual Thing by
making an actual page all the time
potentially from scratch maybe having to
make three or four different pages you
make this page that does this now make
another page that does this plus this
other thing now make another page that
does that plus something else and then
you aggregate their knowledge by
layering on so that they get constant
repetition or redundancy in the stuff
they've already covered so that by the
time that they're producing this really
amazing web page the thing that they
remember the least is the thing they
most recently did but but at that point
it kept but that is not how the pre code
Camp stuff was set up it was set up to
go do this and then do this and then do
this and all of the online for Education
things like the gamified education and
there's a bunch I'm not even going to
say there's a bunch of gamified
Education right now regarding these
kinds of things and the thing I worry
about the most um is that someone's
going to fin enough to do the thing
another good example is vim Adventures
Vim Adventures teaches you how to win
the game Vim Adventures it doesn't teach
you vim and kids that had gone through
Vim Adventures did not know how to edit
a file using Vim in the terminal they
had no idea because they never
Associated the act of editing a file
with the keystrokes that were happening
from Vim adventures and the idea the
idea the hypothesis behind a thing like
them Adventures is oh these kids are
going to master all these really you
know command line things the problem is
that's not how your brain works your
brain works by associating the task at
hand with what you seeing that means
you're looking at a terminal and you
have a text file that needs to be edited
what are the commands and then your
fingers become associated with the
movements and stuff to do that and that
is exactly the same thing for web
development if they had learned how to
make a very simple web page and if I had
walked them through using VSS code or
whatever to make an actual web page the
same way way an actual professional
developer would do it then they would be
building on actual skills using real
tools and I cannot overstate how
valuable that is because even if you
learn the skill completely and you're
doing it in the cloud on some
educational website and you're not
actually logging into a system where
every single thing is the same then the
pneumatic path the the pneumatic
Pathways in your brain neural Pathways
and pneumatic uh pneumatic methods and
stuff like that they're not going to
work because your your brain is is used
to associating all of this stuff the
entire experience it's not just
about knowing how to do X and Y command
it's about having all the pieces be in
sync so that when you are put in a
similar situation for real it's the same
because you've never done anything but
the real thing and and I I see this all
the time and I just I just so my concern
was my concern very very simply is
that uh you know places like prec cod
camp and other gamified education things
there are a couple of areas where I've
seen it more productive than others for
example um code combat uh that because
they were doing coding and they had to
you know the actual syntax of the code
that they were writing um you know they
got they got better at writing that
syntax but but they weren't solving real
world problems they were solving you
know a problem to help them beat beat
the the monster so maybe they learned
how to do recursion in a loop or
something but it wasn't as effective in
my opinion had they been you know
solving their own problems I want to
make uh a story game I want to make a a
something that accomplishes a particular
goal of mine and and that just it's just
much more visceral it's much more real
it just tends to stick better so that's
the end of the video really um I it's
not to throw Rico Camp under the bus I
understand that they have changed a lot
but um the takeaway was I sent 45 people
through free C Camp and only two of them
could build a website afterwards a web
page and those two had already learned
how to do it before that that's the
truth